Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be learning
how to calculate formal charge.
So what is formal charge,
or what is it used for?
This is a way for us to be able to
validate our Lewis structures and
to make sure that we are creating
what is considered the lowest energy
structure, meaning what is considered
to be the most correct structure.
Now when we use the word charge, this
is a little bit of a misnomer, meaning
that it's a little misleading leading.
These are generally what
we consider fake charges.
They allow us to just be able to
figure out what is the low, what
is the most likely structure.
So it's another tip, another way
to be able to have another tool
in your little canvas toolbox.
How to figure out all these
little missing pieces.
The formal charge, what?
It uses a very simple formula
when it's all based on what
our valence electrons are.
And our Lewis structure
that we are drawing.
So its formal charge is equal to the
number of valence electrons, minus
the number of lone pair electrons
that you have drawn around an atom.
So for example, if I were to draw a,
let's say, um, let's say hydrogen for
example, and I have just one little.here.
Well, the way that that would work is,
well, we have one valence electron.
We have one lone pair electron, and
it's making no bonds at the moment.
So this would be a formal charge of zero.
So the last little part is valence
electrons minus lone pairs, and
then that's gonna be minus the
number of bonds around the atom.
So it's kind of taking into consideration
all these little parts here.
So we're just counting what we have.
And the goal here is when we're looking
at these, just to remember, is that.
These are not real charges.
This allows us to figure out what the
correct Lewis structure is, because
the goal here is to have what I would
consider to be the smallest, um,
essentially the smallest possible charge
on each of these different atoms, right?
If you calculate it and you get a
number that's two or three, that's
a very large, you wanna try to have
zeros and ones, and that tells you
that your structure is correct.
It also should match up what
your ionic charge is for
your entire molecule as well.
So it is related to the real
charge if you have an ion.
So it's just another method.
Um, the big thing is though too, is
this helps give chemists and biologists
insight into the chemical reactivity.
So if something has a negative or a
positive charge, or if it has a lonely
electron, this gives us some insight
on what is happening in the molecule.
And this pairs very well with the, the,
uh, with octet rule violations or octet
rule exceptions, which is gonna be in
a follow-up video to this one and how
exactly they can kind of pair together.
So let's take a look at a bunch
of different examples here of how
we can use this for ourselves.
And you can add this as another tool
to be able to write Lewis structures.
is what we are going to be doing.
So the first thing is whenever we have
a Lewis structure and any of these
covalent bonded molecules, typically
the central atom is always written
first when we have a molecular formula.
So nitrogen would be the center here.
From knowing our valence electrons,
from looking at the periodic table,
it has five different valence
electrons, whereas hydrogen, right?
And we have three of them that are
bonding as one valence electron.
Uh, one tip that I always have is to line
them up with all the lonely electrons.
So we're gonna put all these
hydrogens in just like so.
Okay.
And then we are going to bond
them together by connecting them.
Okay, so what we have here
is ammonia being connected.
So that's the name of this molecule.
And what we are actually gonna
do now is calculate what the
formal charge is for each element.
Now being that we only have two
different types of elements, it's a
very quick little calculation for each.
So let's start with nitrogen.
So the first thing is how many
valence electrons did it have?
So it started with five
valent electrons, right?
Nitrogen has five.
Now the question is how many lone
pair electrons does this have?
And you can see here is, okay,
we have two lone pair electrons
that are near this structure.
So what we are going to
do is five minus two.
Now the next thing is, is we're going
to subtract the number of bonds we have.
So it's lone pair electrons minus bonds.
So we have five minus two minus three,
and you can quickly do this math in
your head, which is the best part.
You do not need to calculate.
The five minus two is three.
Three minus three is zero.
So what does that tell
you about this molecule?
Well, it tells you that
it's formal charge is zero.
So what we could do is just write a little
zero next to our nitrogen, which is good.
You want to have something that's
as close to zero as possible.
Zero is perfect.
That's letting you know, all
right, we got what we want.
Um, now that doesn't always mean
that you have the final structure.
You gotta check everything.
But the goal is to have as low of
numbers when everything is possible.
Ideally, one zeros, one plus ones.
And so if we do hydrogen, which
is the same thing on all of these.
We're gonna do this exact same thing.
So we have one valence electron, we have
zero lone pairs on hydrogen, and then
we have one bond that's being formed.
So once again, you can do one minus
one, and you see a charge of zero.
What this telling you is all of the
hydrogens have a zero formal charge.
This is your correct Lewis structure.
It's a way to check your work.
So let's go on to another example.
We have four valence
electrons around carbon.
So we're gonna write four dots.
Now we're gonna connect all the pieces.
So one thing is being that carbon has
a tendency to make four bonds, you can
notice that you have four different
element or four atoms that are here.
So we're going to be
connecting all of them.
So let's use a different color here for
hydrogen, we'll do purple for hydrogen.
We'll line them up with the sides.
And it doesn't matter
which side you choose.
So if you choose like on, let's
say you wanted to put one on the
right, that's fine, as long as you
kind of put them all, as long as
you have the right number of them.
So now we have our fluorine.
This has seven balanced electrons.
We're gonna put seven dots around it.
And now what we're going to do
is connect all of our bonds.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4.
Carbon has a tendency to make four bonds.
Hydrogen has a tendency to make one.
Deploying also has a tendency to make one.
All those are happy.
Now, do you always have to
check your, your formal charge?
You don't always, but it's something that
gives you kind of like a second check.
So what we'll do is, for all of
them, let's do them individually.
So we have carbon is the first one.
There's four valence electrons, zero
lone pairs, and then four bonds.
So we have four minus four is zero.
Now for hydrogen, it's
gonna be the same idea.
So all the hydrogens that are here, we
have one valence electron that started
with, it has zero lone pairs and it's
making one bond that's also zero.
And then if we check for fluorine,
well, it's gonna be the kinda same idea.
We had seven valence electrons.
We started with, we have, we
essentially have six lone pair
electrons and one bond that is here.
So we have also zero.
Stone you.
If wondering, where the
heck did I get six from?
Well being, there's 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6 dots around flooring.
Okay?
So it's checking our work.
And you notice that they're all zeroes.
It's telling you, okay, what you drew
is correct a way to check your work.
Let's go on to another.
Okay?
So sometimes with these structures
that can be a little bit more tricky in
trying to figure out how they are bonded.
So we have ho no, which is for this one.
A lot of molecules are written.
How they're bonded, meaning kind of
like how they're bonded in order.
So we're gonna do the same China
idea and going off our bond trends,
we can kind of plug in our pieces.
So I've been, I kind of mentioned that
before and if you've seen my previous
videos and you kind of might already
know, is that there are bond trends.
So hydrogen always makes one bond.
Uh, nitrogen always makes three bonds.
Oxygen always makes two bonds.
Then in earlier we saw, okay, carbon
made for, and the halogens have all been
making, uh, been making, uh, one bond.
So we have trends that we can follow here.
So what we're gonna do is we're going
to be making, uh, this bonded in order.
We're gonna start with
hydrogen on the far side.
We're gonna put the one dot, we're
then going to put in oxygen next.
We got oxygen, and that has six
dots around it, just like so.
Then we're going to put in nitrogen,
which has five dots all around
it, and then we have oxygen,
which also has six dots around it.
Okay?
Everything's lined up just
like the way we want it now.
What we're now going to do is
connect all of our pieces and then
we'll verify using formal charge.
So we'll connect hydrogen oxygen.
That one's easy being that
hydrogen always makes one bond.
So now oxygen needs to make one
more bond, make itself happy.
So why don't we make it
with the nitrogen next door?
All right, so this now has eight
valence electrons around Oxygen, and
we can even try to see like, okay,
when we do formal charge, you'll see.
Does that make sense?
Uh, for when we are doing it now
for oxygen, as I said, this has
a tendency to make two bonds.
Nitrogen has a tendency to make three.
So what we can quickly do for ourselves
is rearrange this and make a tr
or a double bond between nitrogen
and oxygen and connect them all.
Now, is this right?
This is where formal charge can help us.
Is this, does the structure make sense?
So hydrogen, we're gonna
do the same math, right?
It started with one valence electron.
It has no lone pairs.
It's making one bond.
That means it has a number of zero.
So, so far that looks good.
Now we are gonna switch to oxygen.
So the oxygen on the left, so
we'll put a little L next to it.
Let's say the left one, it has six valence
electrons, it has four lone pairs, and
on top of that we are making two bonds.
So we have a six minus six,
which is equal to zero.
Okay?
So put a little zero over top.
Nitrogen had five valence electrons,
has two lone pairs, and it's
currently making three bonds.
So we have another zero
of, so far, so good.
Everything has zeros now.
For the right oxygen, I'll put or just to
denote, Hey, we're doing the right one.
And this one's gonna be the same idea.
So we have six minus four minus two,
and once again, that is equal to zero.
So the four lone, four lone pair
electrons, two bonds around it, everything
is, they all have zero across the board.
That's the goal on you A, you
have the correct structure.
Let's go on to another example.
Okay, so for this question, draw the
Lewis structure for the sulfate ion.
Now this is one of the places where
the formal charges are gonna help
you realize what the ionic charge is.
So here sulfate has an ionic charge.
A two minus is not the same thing
as formal charge, but it allows
you to be able to see how are
the charges really distributed.
Now the big thing about these is the char.
The real charge favors electronegative
elements, meaning things that are up
into the right of the periodic table.
So close the fluorine.
Now with this one, the thing
about it, sulfur is an octet rule.
Violator meaning it likes to expand what?
It's a avail, what is available to it.
So being that sulfur has six
valence electrons, it can utilize
the vacant D orbital to allow
for more things to bond to it.
So what do is all that mean?
What we're going to do
is we're going to place.
Six electrons around it.
So we got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and six, just like so.
And we are going to put our
oxygen around on all sides.
So we're gonna have oxygen on
the left, right, top, middle,
and bottom, just like so.
Now the thing is, how do we know
how many bonds we're gonna have?
How does this work?
So this is where our trick that I learned
that really helps me remember these,
and it has to do with understanding.
How double bonds and single bonds
work with formal charge for oxygen.
So for oxygen, if I have
oxygen, that's a double bond.
So let's say if I put in a double bond
around, uh, one of these different
atoms here, so we're gonna connect this.
How does that work when
it comes to formal charge?
Well, oxygen has six valence electrons.
Right now it has four lone
pairs, so I'm gonna put those
in white so we can see them.
And then we have two bonds
that are being formed.
Code six minus four is equal
to zero, so it has a formal
charge of zero, which is great.
That's what one of the
things that we want here.
We want a formal charge zero.
Now what about O as a single bond?
So let's do O single.
So meaning, let's say if I were to
put in my dots for this oxygen over
here, and I'm just going to put one dot
on the side, how does this one work?
Well, OS single has essentially six
minus six lone pairs that I put in here.
I added an extra one minus one
bond that's here, so this is
a negative one formal charge.
So what this tells you is that the
structure is going to have two single
bonds, two double bonds, because
we need to make a overall charge
of negative two on the structure.
It's something that helps you
predict what you are going to
have when you are to draw these.
Now, do you always, will you
always remember those strengths?
Potentially?
No.
So one of the things for when we
are trying to write these right is
so starting over with ourselves.
So keep that in mind that we're gonna
prove that we have this double single
bonds that we have on the side.
So it all comes down to being able
to first for sulfur is know how
many valence electrons you have.
You have six valence electrons for oxygen.
We have six valence electrons.
We have a total of four atoms.
And then we have two extra electrons
that we need to to keep in mind.
So how many total do we have?
Well, we are going to have a total
of 32 electrons that need to be
distributed in this structure.
So when we are going to show this, the
first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna write down our sulfur, which
has our six electrons all around it.
Now we're going to put in our oxygens.
So we put in 1, 2, 3, put in
our six electrons on all sides,
just like so.
Now really the thing is that
we're supposed to do first.
Separate our look, or essentially
just connect everything as if it was
just making one single bond first.
So we're gonna connect the oxygen,
the sulfur, the oxygen, the sulfur,
just like this with single bonds.
And now the issue with this is that
we see that we have extra electrons
that exist within our molecule.
So we have all of our single bonds, and
then we have two electrons that aren't
doing anything on the middle of sulfur.
You also have multiple electrons
that aren't doing anything with
the other structures as well.
So this is where we're going
to be making some double bonds.
So let's make our double bonds with
two of the oxygens and that that's
all that sulfur is capable of doing.
We'll make one on the left,
one on the right, just like so.
I've reorganized this a little bit
just to make it look a little lighter.
Okay.
So we have our structure just like
so, and what we are going to now do is
mean that we have two extra electrons.
You first want to add them
to the external atoms first.
So what we are going to do
is, and that's to complete any
octets where they are needed.
So we can see that two of the
oxygens don't have a complete octet.
So this is really the general
idea for trying to show.
This ionic species having a two-minus
charge overall, but is it correct?
Well, if you remember from
earlier, we proved to ourselves
what double singles have.
So if you notice we have two double bonds.
So we have one on the right-hand
side, one on the left, and then we
have two single bonds, one on the
lower portion, one on one on the top.
So this is showing you, hey, your
formal charge is currently being paid.
What about sulfur?
It's sulfur happy the way it is.
Well, it has six valence electrons and
it's currently making, it has zero lone
pairs and six bonds, so it has a zero.
So what we can see is okay for each
of the single bonds, we have negative
one, we have zero on all the structures
and all the elements in the middle.
So it's a happy structure.
Now is this the only way to draw it?
And one thing that you might see
peeking on the bottom is this is
where something known as a resonance
structure can peek its head up.
Meaning that the doubles and single
bonds, they can change positions
and lead to potentially different
structures that are possible.
Meaning that, let's say if I were
to draw my molecule of sulfate.
Why did I pick the double
bonds on the sides?
Like the way that I showed it before,
could I have drawn them where they were
on, let's say, the left and the right?
Um, or sorry, on the top and the bottom.
Why did I choose that?
So resonance is all about where
double bonds could potentially switch
positions, just like the one that
I have down here on the bottom.
Where there's multiple different places
where you can place double bonds.
Um, maybe if I wanted to potentially
place them where it had sulfur, had a
double bond on top, a double bond on
the side, single bond, and a single bond
on the other part, you have different
options available for resonance and
that's sometimes that can happen.
And the whole idea is because
every atom is unique, they can
switch to different locations.
So when you have these alternating
double and single bonds, something
new is resonant structure as possible.
Okay.
It's still all based
on your formal charges.
Okay.
Our last question, which
resonance structure is the most
common for the cyanate ion?
So here I have the cyanate ion, and we're
gonna look at this concept of resonance.
So below I have three different
resonance structures that are drawn.
I have the first one, second
one, and the third one.
And what each one of these, as you can
see, is, looks a little bit different.
Different number of double bonds,
different number of triple bonds.
And what we're going to do is
using formal charge is determine
which one would be the, the most
likely one that you're gonna see.
The thing with resonance is they're
all possible, but that doesn't mean
that it's gonna be, there might be
a preference for one versus another.
So, and this is something that gives
you an idea about chemical reactivity.
So something with a negative charge
and it has many resonance structures.
Usually you see it in a lot of different
reactions, or maybe it could be something
that's very stable and used for all
kinds of pharmaceutical reasons, helps
stabilize maybe a drug or so as well.
So before, right when we were doing
all these, right, the how we calculated
charges was we did the valence electrons.
So if we do oxygen, we have six.
Then we have right now on this
first structure, we have, uh, four
lone pairs that are all around it.
So it'd be six minus four, and
then it's making two bonds.
We have six minus four minus
two, so this is equal to zero.
Okay, great.
Now we'll do the same thing
with carbon in the middle.
So carbon is, has four valence
electrons as zero lone pairs on
it, and it's making four bonds.
So this is also zero.
Fantastic.
Just like we want.
Now, if we look at nitrogen
on the far right hand side,
it has five ounce electrons.
It has four lone pair electrons and two
bonds that are currently being formed.
So how, how much is that?
Well, this has a negative one charge
to it, so we'll have a negative here.
Okay, great.
So we have zero.
Zero negative.
Looks fantastic.
Let's look at the next one.
So with this structure,
we have oxygen again.
So oxygen is making a
triple bond in this one.
So let's check our math.
So it'd be O, We have six
minus two lone pairs, and then
it's making three bonds on it.
Three.
This is going to be a positive one
charge, so six minus five positive one.
Now with carbon in the middle,
right, it's gonna be the same
idea as what we had before.
We have four valence electrons, minus
zero lone pairs, and then four bonds.
So this is gonna have a zero charge.
Then for nitrogen, we got six
valence electrons, six lone pair
electrons, and then one bond.
This is going to be a.
Negative one, or, sorry, I
did the math a little bit.
Correct.
Here we have five ounce
electrons, minus six minus one.
So this is gonna be a negative
two overall formal charge.
Now, is that okay?
Well, it is a resonance structure.
It is possible, but if you remember from
the beginning of the video, the goal
was to have the lowest number possible.
Two is actually considered very high.
You want zeros and one, so most likely
this will probably be the least.
Common structure out of all of 'em.
Okay.
It's possible, but it's
gonna be very unfavorable.
Okay, last one.
Let's do the last O.
So O, we have six minus six
valence electrons, or sorry,
lone pairs minus one bond.
We have negative one, a negative one here.
And then for carbon we have
four minus zero minus four.
That's gonna be over zero.
Then for nitrogen, we have five valence
electrons, two lone pairs, re bonds.
So zero.
So we have zero, zero negative one.
So what are we gonna compare?
We're gonna be comparing essentially the
first structure and the third structure.
So let's kind of rearrange
some things here.
Let's kind of rearrange it and
what we're gonna be looking at
here is between one and three.
So what's, which one would be
the more favorable outta the two?
Well, they both have
a negative one charge.
One of them is on nitrogen,
the other one is on oxygen.
So which one is more likely?
Well, this is where we're gonna
be learning about something
known as electronegativity.
So in my other videos, we're gonna have
learn about Electronegativity and what
that's all about is a periodic trend.
Essentially, if we have a periodic table.
The more you go up into the right of the
periodic table, the more negative those
elements tend to be when they are bonding.
Meaning they are a little bit greedier
when they wanna take in their electrons.
So oxygen is a little bit more
up and right, the nitrogen.
So the most likely structure
is going to be number three.
Okay, so this would be the
most common number one would
be the second most common.
Number two would be the least common.
So resonance say, all exist.
Let's us.
Which one is the most likely?
And you can also think too, you
can see your bonding trends, right?
Nitrous three bonds has the three
bonds here, however, one, four,
but oxygen usually wants to make.
So it's all about which one, correct?
All.
Okay.
So this has been formal charge.
I know it was a little bit of practice
within a little bit longer, but it
goes through all different types.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped a little bit.